Indiana University Office of Military Information records, 1940-1946 C31
Indiana University Archives
Indiana University Office of Military Information records
1940-1946
1942-1945
Indiana University Archives
Indiana University. Office of Military Information
C31
2 cubic feet
The Office of Military Information was created 1 July 1942 at Indiana University to advise students, parents, faculty members and the general public about war service opportunities and regulations. Collection consists of subject files arranged alphabetically and spans the years 1942-1946. The collection includes correspondence with military and university personnel, directives from Washington, D.C. and regional military offices, and information on housing, courses, and instructors.
Access Restrictions
Files containing student records are closed to researchers.
Advance notice for access is required.
Historical Note
The Office of Military Information was created 1 July 1942 at Indiana University to advise students, parents, faculty members, and the general public about war service opportunities and regulations. Indiana University hosted several programs during World War II to prepare young men and women for military and civil service. Several of these programs placed students on inactive duty in the military until the completion of the program, at which time they were placed on active duty.
United States Naval Training School (June 1942 - May 1944) prepared men and women for service in the Navy, the Coast Guard, and the Marine Corps. Two specialized Naval training programs offered additional training. The V- 12 unit furnished training for medical and dental students. The V-7 program, open to juniors and seniors, required two semesters of mathematics and one course in plane trigonometry.
Other programs included the Army Enlisted Reserve Corps (ERC) which accepted men between 18 and 45 years of age. Requirements for the ERC consisted of passing the officers' candidate physical exam and being a United States citizen who had not received a bachelors' degree. The Army Specialized Training Program (June 1943 - March 1946) focussed upon basic engineering and foreign area and language education. In September 1942, the Women's Auxiliary Training Corps (WATC) furnished female students with training which prepared them for service in one of the various women's reserves organizations.
With peace declared in 1945, the Office of Military Information had served its war-time mission and was dissolved in 1947.
Arrangement
The collection is organized in a single series, Subject files, arranged alphabetically.
Scope and Content Note
The collection consists of subject files arranged alphabetically and spans the years 1940-1946. It is comprised primarily of the files of the Office of Military Information Director Frank E. Horack. Professor Horack acted in this capacity on two separate occasions: June 1942-August 1943 and July 1944-1947. In the interim Professor Horack served as Coordinator, War Service Programs, from 1943 to 1945 and these materials are also in the collection. Also present are the papers of Harold F. Lusk, who acted as Director of the Office of Military Information from September 1943 to June 1944.
The files contain: correspondence with military and university personnel; directives from Washington, D.C. and regional military offices; and information on housing, courses, and instructors. A significant correspondent with the Office of Military Information was Herman T. Briscoe in his role as consultant to the Division of Professional and Technical Training, War Manpower Commission, Washington, D.C.
Included in the collection are three folders containing confidential information regarding students enrolled in the various programs. These are at the end of box 2 and are closed to researchers.
Acquisition Information
Accession 1118.
World War, 1939-1945 --Education and the war.; World War, 1939-1945 --War work --Schools.; World War, 1939-1945 --Indiana --Bloomington.; Military education --Indiana --Bloomington --History --20th century --Sources.; Horack, Frank E., Jr. (Frank Edward), 1907-1957 -- Archives; Indiana University. Office of Military Information -- Archives; Indiana University. Office of Military Information -- Records and correspondence; Indiana University. Office of Military Information -- History -- Sources; Horack, Frank E., Jr. (Frank Edward), 1907-1957 -- Correspondence; Horack, Frank E., Jr. (Frank Edward), 1907-1957 -- Correspondence -- Selections; Lusk, Harold F., 1893-1976 -- Archives; Lusk, Harold F., 1893-1976 -- Correspondence; Lusk, Harold F., 1893-1976 -- Correspondence -- Selections
- Subject files, 1940-1946
  - Army Specialized Training Program (ASTP)
    - Achievement Examinations, 1943-1945 (Box 1)
    - Contract (Box 1)
      - 1943 (Box 1)
      - 1944 (Box 1)
      - 1945-1946 (Box 1)
    - Directives, 1942-1944 (Box 1)
    - General (Box 1)
      - 1943, (2 folders) (Box 1)
      - 1944, (2 folders) (Box 1)
      - 1945 (Box 1)
    - Graduation Exercises, 1943-1944 (Box 1)
    - Instructors, 1943-1945 (Box 1)
    - Manuals, 1944 (Box 1)
    - Rating Students, undated (Box 1)
  - Army Specialized Training Reserve Program (ASTRP), 1943-1945 (Box 1)
  - Area and Language Studies (Box 1)
    - 1943 (Box 1)
    - 1944 (Box 1)
    - 1944-1945 (Box 1)
  - Army Officer Procurement, 1942-1944 (Box 1)
  - Briscoe, Herman T. (Washington, D.C.), 1942-1943 (Box 1)
  - Civil Affairs Training Program (CAT), 1944 (Box 1)
  - Civil Service, 1942-1943 (Box 1)
  - Class V-7 - U.S. Naval Reserve, 1941-1943 (Box 1)
  - Crawford, William H. (Dean, I.U. School of Dentistry), 1943-1944 (Box 1)
  - Curricula (Box 1)
    - ASTP, ASTRP, 1943-1944; (3 folders) (Box 1)
    - Correspondence, 1943-1945 (Box 1)
  - Dental Students/Graduates, 1943-1944 (Box 1)
  - Dowling, Leo R. (School of Business Administration), Dec. 1943 (Box 2)
  - ERC (Enlisted Reserve Corps), 1942-1944 (Box 2)
  - ERC (Enlisted Reserve Corps) (Box 2)
    - Correspondence, 1940-1943 (Box 2)
    - General, 1942-1944 (Box 2)
  - Gatch, W. D. (Dean, I.U. Medical School), 1942-1945 (Box 2)
  - Housing, 1943 (Box 2)
  - Intensive Training Programs, 1942-1943 (Box 2)
  - Joint Army - Navy Program, 1942-1943 (Box 2)
  - Keene, Archie T. (President, Indiana Technical College), 1943-1944 (Box 2)
  - Marine Corps, 1942-1943 (Box 2)
  - Merchant Marine Cadet Corps, 1942 (Box 2)
  - Meteorology, 1942-1943 (Box 2)
  - Military Government Training (Box 2)
    - General, 1942-1944; (3 folders) (Box 2)
    - IU Resources, undated (Box 2)
  - Military Status of Students, 1942-1945 (Box 2)
  - National Roster of Scientific and Specialized Personnel (Box 2)
    - General, 1943-1945 (Box 2)
    - New Procedures, 1943-1944 (Box 2)
  - Naval Training School, 1942-1944 (Box 2)
  - V-12 Unit (Greencastle) (Navy College Training Program), 1943-1945 (Box 2)
  - Navy Lists, 1943 (Box 2)
  - Navy V-1 College Manual, undated (Box 2)
  - Navy - Office Procurement, 1942-1943 (Box 2)
  - Office of Naval Officer Procurement, 1942-1945 (Box 2)
  - Office of Scientific Research and Development (OSRD), 1943-1945 (Box 2)
  - Pre-AST File, 1942 (Box 2)
  - Pre-Flight Training Program, 1942-1943 (Box 2)
  - Publications - General, 1941-1945 (Box 2)
  - Qualifying Examinations, 1943-1945 (Box 2)
  - Questionnaires of Men Enlisted in the Naval Reserves, undated (Box 2)
  - ROTC (Reserve Officer Training Corps), 1943-1945 (Box 2)
  - Robinson, Tom (Frankfort, IN), undated (Box 2)
  - Russell, N. C. (Lt. Cdr. USNR), 1942-1943 (Box 2)
  - Russian Language Program (Box 2)
    - General, 1945 (Box 2)
    - Instructors, 1945 (Box 2)
  - Signal Corps, 1942-1943 (Box 2)
  - State Selective Service Headquarters, 1942-1946 (Box 2)
  - University Housing Plan, undated (Box 2)
  - WATC (Women's Auxiliary Training Program), 1942-1943 (Box 2)
  - War Manpower Commission, 1941-1944 (Box 3)
  - Basic Engineering Program, 1943; (folder 1 of 2) (Box 3)
  - Basic Engineering Program, 1943; (folder 2 of 2) (Box 3)
    Conditions Governing Access
    Restricted
  - Marine Corps List, 1942-1944; (folder 1 of 2) (Box 3)
  - Marine Corps List, 1942-1944; (folder 2 of 2) (Box 3)
  - Medical and Dental, 1943-1946; (3 folders) (Box 3)
  - Medical/Dental - Bloomington, 1943-1944; (folder 1 of 2) (Box 3)
  - Medical/Dental - Bloomington, 1943-1944; (folder 2 of 2) (Box 3)